Shakespear Family mss., 1776-1965 LMC 1876
Lilly Library
Shakespear Family mss.
1776-1965
Lilly Library
LMC 1876
3 Boxes 3 custom
The Shakespear family mss., 1825-1944, consists of the correspondence and papers of the families of Olivia Tucker Shakespear, 1863-1938, and her daughter, Dorothy Shakespear Pound, 1886-1973.
Conditions Governing Access
This collection is open for research.
Many collections are housed offsite; retrieval requires advance notice. Please make an appointment a minimum of one week in advance of your visit.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Purchase: 1991-1993
Biographical Note
Dorothy Shakespear Pound (1886-1973) was born in London, England, on 14 September 1886 to lawyer Henry Hope Shakespear (1849-1923) and novelist Olivia Tucker Shakespear (1863-1938). She met American poet Ezra Pound (1885-1972) on 16 February 1909, at one of her mother's literary salons, and the two married on 20 April 1914. Her vorticist paintings were featured in several Modernist publications and advertisements in the early 20th century. The Pounds' son, Omar (1926-2010), was born on 10 September 1926 and was raised in England by Dorothy's mother. Dorothy and Ezra lived in Paris in the early 1920s, in Italy from 1925 to 1945, and in the United States from 1945 to 1958, when they returned to Italy. In 1961, Dorothy moved to London, where she died on 8 December 1973.
Scope and Contents
I. Biographical materials includes any materials related to laying out the family tree of the Shakespear family and their family branches. II. Correspondence includes the letters to and from family members, including some letters from Ezra Pound to his mother-in-law, Olivia Shakespear. III. Printed includes various printed materials about family members. IV. Writings includes drafts and manuscripts of various pieces of writings, mostly from Olivia Shakespear. Miscellaneous includes all other items, including various legal papers, drawings, photographs, and some hair.
Arrangement
This collection is arranged into the following series: I. Biographical material, II. Correspondence, III. Printed, IV. Writings, and V. Miscellaneous.
Related Materials
See Pound mss., also located at the Lilly Library, Indiana University, Bloomington, Indiana.
British literature; Family trees; Pound, Dorothy; Shakespear, Olivia; Pound, Ezra, 1885-1972
- I. BIOGRAPHICAL MATERIALS
  - Auchmuty family
  - Blake family
  - Bruère family
  - Donnellon/Russell/Tayler/Twycross families
  - Roulston family
  - Johnson family
  - Lour family
  - Muirson family
  - Mulcaster family
  - Shakespear [sic] family I - Pedigree by Sir Thomas Phillippe
  - Shakespear family II - Shakespeare of Stepney Table XIII
  - Shakespear family III - The Tabbot line
  - Shakespear family IV - Alexander Shakespear 1821-1884
  - Shakespear family V - Alexander Shakespear 1821-1884, Avery's ancestral tablet
  - Shakespear family VI - Alexander Muirson Wake Shakespeare 1855-1927, Avery's ancestral tablet
  - Shakespear family VII - Catherine Helen Augusta Shakespear 1947-1917, Avery's ancestral tablet
  - Shakespear family VIII - Colin Shakespear 1764-1835
  - Shakespear family IX - Henry Davenport Shakespear 1786-1838
  - Shakespear family X - Louisa (Shakespear) Higginson 1812-1844
  - Shakespear family XI
  - Shakespear family XII
  - Thackeray, Thomas 1789-1814
  - Tucker family I
  - Tucker family II
  - Tucker family III
  - Tucker family IV
  - Tucker family V
  - Tucker family VI
  - Tucker family VII
  - Tucker family VIII
  - Tucker family IX
  - Tucker family X
  - Vizard family
- II. CORRESPONDENCE
  - 1776
  - 1797-1828
  - - Certificate of baptism of Catherine Mary Tayler, 1828 Feb. 15
  - 1829-1838
  - 1839-1849
  - - R.H. Rattray to Sir Charles Metcalfe, 1938, July 11
  - 1850
  - 1851-1859
  - 1860
  - 1861-1873
  - 1874-1881
  - - Indenture, 1881, Jan. 5
  - 1882-1885
  - 1886-1889
  - - Account book with Lloyd Bank oh H.H. Shakespear, 1889, Jan. 1 - 1897, Oct. 5
  - 1890-1895
  - - Will of Henry Hape Shakespear, 1895, Feb. 25
  - 1896-1899
  - 1900
  - - Account book for H.T. Tucker, 1900, Aug. 27-1917 Nov
  - 1901-1902
  - 1902, Mar. 20
  - 1903-1910
  - 1911-1915
  - 1916-1919
  - 1920-1921
  - - Agreement of partnership, 1921, Jan.31
  - 1922
  - 1922, Jan. 24
  - 1922, July
  - 1923-1924
  - - Olivia Shakespear to W. B. Yeats, 1923, Nov. 16-1935, July 18
  - 1925-1934
  - - Frederic Manning to Olivia Shakespear, 1934, July 22
  - 1935-1938
  - 1939-1965
  - Ezra Pound to Olivia Shakespeare, 1910-1925
  - Ezra Pound to Olivia Shakespeare, 1926-1930
  - Ezra Pound to Olivia Shakespeare, 1931-1935
  - Ezra Pound to Olivia Shakespeare, 1936-1940
  - Ezra Pound to Olivia Shakespeare Misc
  - No date
- III. PRINTED
  - The Trial of Henry St. George Tucker, 1810-1821
  - The Mutiny of the Bengal Army, 1857
  - Rules for the Committee of the Shakespear's Students Aiding Society, 1873
  - The Order for the Burial of the Dead: Henry Tod Tucker, 1896 Aug.
  - Indian Civil Service Dinner Club pamphlet, 1908, June 11
  - East and West, [1908?]
  - Prospectus of a Booke to be Called John Shakespear of Shadwell, 1931, June 10
  - H.V.F. Winstone's Captain Shakespear review, 1975-1976
  - "Bermuda in 1976" in History Today, 1976, July
  - Olivia Shakespear and W. B. Yeats by William harwood, 1986
- IV. WRITINGS
  - "...And Thus in Connecticut" (Box 2)
  - "The Aspect of Renunciation" (Box 2)
  - Authors, Presidents, Words (Box 2)
  - Beauty's Hour: A Phantasy (Box 2)
  - The Devotees manuscript, bounded (Box 2)
  - The Devotees review (Box 2)
  - Glossary (Box 2)
  - Note: Bauque from Voltaire (Box 2)
  - Verses - Tucker, Henry Tudor (Box 2)
- V. MISCELLANEOUS
  - Address book (Box 2)
  - Art collection, 1835-1911 (Box 2)
  - Blossom, 1845, June 30 (Box 2)
  - Buddhism (Box 2)
  - Drawings (Box 2)
  - Hair (Box 2)
  - Heather, White (Box 3)
  - Horoscope (Box 3)
  - Marriage settlement (Box 3)
  - Photographs (Box 3)
  - Piscataway Town Book (Box 3)
  - Shakespear, Alexander I - Career...Bengal Civil Service (Box 3)
  - Shakespear, Alexander II - Legal papers re. Will and testament (Box 3)
  - Shakespear, Catherine Mary (Tayler) (Box 3)
  - Shakespear, Henry Hape I - Papers relating to his estate (Box 3)
  - Shakespear, Henry Hape II - Trinity Hall notebook (Box 3)
  - Tucker, Henry Tod (Box 3)
  - Tucker, Henry Tudor (Box 3)
  - Tucker, Thomas Tudor (Box 3)
  - Vizard papers, 1874-1878 (Box 3)
  - Vizard papers, 1879-1881 (Box 3)
  - Vizard papers, 1882 (Box 3)
  - Vizard papers, 1883-1884 (Box 3)
  - Vizard papers n.d. (Box 3)